<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-11-10T22:19:56+07:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Blockchain</title><subtitle>Blockchain</subtitle><author><name>Nguyen Le Linh</name><email>nglelinh@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">author details</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/home/author-details/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="author details" /><published>2021-05-20T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2021-05-20T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/home/author-details</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/home/author-details/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name>Nguyen Le Linh</name><email>nglelinh@gmail.com</email></author><category term="home" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">References and Resources</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/reference/26_reference/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="References and Resources" /><published>2021-03-28T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2021-03-28T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/reference/26_reference</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/reference/26_reference/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="essential-blockchain-books">Essential Blockchain Books</h2>

<h3 id="primary-textbooks">Primary Textbooks</h3>]]></content><author><name>Nguyen Le Linh</name><email>nglelinh@gmail.com</email></author><category term="reference" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Essential Blockchain Books]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">makers</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/home/makers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="makers" /><published>2021-02-03T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2021-02-03T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/home/makers</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/home/makers/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name>Nguyen Le Linh</name><email>nglelinh@gmail.com</email></author><category term="home" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">contents</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/home/link_to_how_to_contribute/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="contents" /><published>2021-01-27T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2021-01-27T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/home/link_to_how_to_contribute</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/home/link_to_how_to_contribute/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name>Nguyen Le Linh</name><email>nglelinh@gmail.com</email></author><category term="home" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">introduction</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/home/introduction/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="introduction" /><published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/home/introduction</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/home/introduction/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name>Nguyen Le Linh</name><email>nglelinh@gmail.com</email></author><category term="home" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Course Contents</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/home/contents/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Course Contents" /><published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/home/contents</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/home/contents/"><![CDATA[<p>A comprehensive introduction to Blockchain, covering neural network fundamentals, modern architectures (CNNs, RNNs, Transformers), training techniques, generative models, and practical applications in computer vision, natural language processing, and beyond.</p>

<h1 id="course-objectives">Course Objectives</h1>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Provide students with fundamental knowledge of Blockchain theory and practice to support their study and research in data science and AI.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Enable students to understand, implement, and train deep neural networks from scratch and using modern frameworks.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Develop skills in applying Blockchain to real-world problems across various domains including computer vision, NLP, and reinforcement learning.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Prepare students to read and implement cutting-edge research papers and contribute to the advancement of Blockchain.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="main-textbooks">Main Textbooks</h2>

<h3 id="primary-references">Primary References</h3>

<p>Beginner / Conceptual</p>

<p>The Basics of Bitcoins and Blockchains by Antony Lewis — A clear, non-technical introduction to cryptocurrencies + blockchain. 
MIT OpenCourseWare
+3
Investopedia
+3
insights.btoes.com
+3</p>

<p>Blockchain Basics: A Non‑Technical Introduction in 25 Steps by Daniel Drescher — Designed for someone with little or no technical background. 
Metana</p>

<p>Blockchain Revolution: How the Technology Behind Bitcoin and Other Cryptocurrencies is Changing the World by Don &amp; Alex Tapscott — Helps you understand how blockchain might impact business, society, etc. 
Metana
+1</p>

<p>Intermediate / Technical</p>

<p>Mastering Blockchain: Inner Workings of Blockchain, from Cryptography and Decentralized Identities, to DeFi, NFTs and Web3 by Imran Bashir — Covers a good chunk of the technical internals (cryptography, consensus, DApps). 
techtarget.com
+1</p>

<p>Blockchain in Action by Bina Ramamurthy — Geared toward actually building decentralized applications, with code and smart-contract examples. 
Manning Publications</p>

<p>Business / Legal / Strategic</p>

<p>The Business Blockchain: Promise, Practice, and Application of the Next Internet Technology by William Mougayar — How blockchain can apply to business models, strategy. 
Goodreads</p>

<p>Blockchain and the Law: The Rule of Code by Primavera De Filippi &amp; Aaron Wright — A deep dive into legal, governance, regulatory dimensions of blockchain. 
Metana</p>]]></content><author><name>Nguyen Le Linh</name><email>nglelinh@gmail.com</email></author><category term="home" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A comprehensive introduction to Blockchain, covering neural network fundamentals, modern architectures (CNNs, RNNs, Transformers), training techniques, generative models, and practical applications in computer vision, natural language processing, and beyond.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="vi"><title type="html">Lecture 07.05: The Future of Blockchain - Trends và Innovations</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/contents/vi/chapter07/blockchain-chapter07/07_05_Future_Blockchain/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lecture 07.05: The Future of Blockchain - Trends và Innovations" /><published>2021-01-08T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2021-01-08T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/contents/vi/chapter07/blockchain-chapter07/07_05_Future_Blockchain</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/contents/vi/chapter07/blockchain-chapter07/07_05_Future_Blockchain/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="lecture-the-future-of-blockchain---trends-và-innovations">Lecture: The Future of Blockchain - Trends và Innovations</h1>

<h2 id="1-concept-overview">1. Concept Overview</h2>

<p>Blockchain technology stands at inflection point, transitioning from experimental phase to mature infrastructure powering real-world applications serving millions. Future trajectory encompasses technical innovations (modular blockchains, zkEVMs, account abstraction), new application domains (decentralized science, regenerative finance, social coordination), regulatory evolution (institutional adoption, compliance frameworks), và philosophical questions về decentralization’s role trong society.</p>

<p>Next decade likely witnesses consolidation around winning architectures whilst continuous innovation at application layer. Ethereum’s rollup-centric roadmap demonstrates one path - monolithic base layer providing security, modular execution layers providing scalability. Alternative visions include application-specific chains (Cosmos ecosystem), shared security models (Polkadot), và novel consensus mechanisms (Solana’s Proof-of-History, Avalanche’s consensus).</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="2-intuitive-understanding">2. Intuitive Understanding</h2>

<p>Blockchain future comparable to internet’s evolution 1990s→2024. Early internet (1990s) slow, difficult to use, limited applications. Skeptics dismissed as niche technology. Yet infrastructure improvements (broadband, mobile, cloud) và killer applications (social media, streaming, e-commerce) drove mass adoption. Similarly, blockchain infrastructure advancing rapidly (L2s, better UX, tooling), applications emerging (DeFi, NFTs, DAOs) suggesting mass adoption possible despite current limitations.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="3-technical-foundation">3. Technical Foundation</h2>

<p><strong>Modular blockchain</strong> architecture separates concerns: execution layer (compute), data availability layer (storage), consensus layer (ordering), settlement layer (finality). Projects like <strong>Celestia</strong> provide data availability separately, enabling rollups post data there instead of expensive Ethereum calldata, reducing costs dramatically whilst maintaining security.</p>

<p><strong>Account abstraction</strong> (ERC-4337) enables smart contract wallets natively, unlocking programmable accounts với features like social recovery, gas sponsorship (meta-transactions), batch operations, và custom security policies. Future wallets will feel như traditional apps whilst being non-custodial.</p>

<p><strong>ZkEVMs</strong> combine zero-knowledge proof efficiency với full EVM compatibility. Projects like <strong>Polygon zkEVM</strong>, <strong>Scroll</strong>, và <strong>zkSync Era</strong> prove entire EVM execution correctly via SNARKs, enabling Ethereum applications run on zkRollups without modification, achieving both scalability và security.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="4-mathematical--cryptographic-formulation">4. Mathematical / Cryptographic Formulation</h2>

<p>Modular scaling potential:</p>

<p>[
\text{TPS}<em>{\text{total}} = n</em>{\text{rollups}} \times n_{\text{shards}} \times \text{TPS}_{\text{base}}
]</p>

<p>With 100 rollups across 64 shards:
[
\text{TPS} = 100 \times 64 \times 15 = 96,000 \text{ TPS}
]</p>

<p>Approaching Visa-scale throughput!</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="5-implementation-insight">5. Implementation Insight</h2>

<p>Future blockchain development emphasizes <strong>composability</strong> - applications combining primitives from multiple protocols seamlessly. DeFi already demonstrates này: single transaction might interact with Uniswap, Aave, Curve, và Yearn simultaneously. Future extends to cross-domain composability - DeFi + NFTs + DAOs + identity interoperating natively.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="6-common-challenges--attacks--trade-offs">6. Common Challenges / Attacks / Trade-offs</h2>

<p>Regulatory uncertainty remains largest wildcard. Clear frameworks could drive institutional adoption, harsh regulations could stifle innovation. Jurisdictional arbitrage likely - innovation concentrates trong friendly jurisdictions, challenging global enforcement.</p>

<p>Quantum computing timeline uncertain. Optimistic estimates suggest 20-30 years before cryptographically relevant quantum computers exist. Pessimistic estimates under 10 years. Blockchain must prepare accordingly, risk catastrophic failure if quantum breakthrough sudden.</p>

<p>User experience remains barrier to mass adoption. Private key management, gas fees, transaction signing, network switching - all friction points versus Web2’s seamlessness. Solutions emerging (account abstraction, fiat on-ramps, gas abstraction) but adoption gradual.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="7-related-concepts">7. Related Concepts</h2>

<p><strong>Decentralized Science (DeSci)</strong> applies blockchain to scientific research - funding through DAOs, publication on decentralized storage, peer review incentivized by tokens, data sharing với provenance tracking. Could accelerate research whilst improving transparency.</p>

<p><strong>Regenerative Finance (ReFi)</strong> uses blockchain for environmental initiatives - carbon credits, biodiversity tracking, impact investing với verifiable outcomes. Potential align economic incentives với planetary health.</p>

<p><strong>Decentralized Social Media</strong> challenges Facebook, Twitter monopolies. Protocols like Lens, Farcaster enable users own social graphs, content, followers. Resistance to censorship, algorithmic transparency, creator monetization without platform fees.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="8--fundamental-papers--whitepapers">8. ⭐ Fundamental Papers / Whitepapers</h2>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Paper</th>
      <th>Year</th>
      <th>Author(s)</th>
      <th>Contribution</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>“Endgame”</strong></td>
      <td>2021</td>
      <td>Vitalik Buterin</td>
      <td>Ethereum’s long-term vision</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>“Modular Blockchains: A Deep Dive”</strong></td>
      <td>2022</td>
      <td>Celestia team</td>
      <td>Modular architecture thesis</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>“Account Abstraction (ERC-4337)”</strong></td>
      <td>2021</td>
      <td>Vitalik Buterin et al.</td>
      <td>Smart contract wallet standard</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>“The Blockchain Trilemma”</strong></td>
      <td>2017</td>
      <td>Vitalik Buterin</td>
      <td>Fundamental trade-off analysis</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<hr />

<h2 id="9--illustrations--visual-references">9. 🎨 Illustrations &amp; Visual References</h2>

<p><img src="https://celestia.org/images/modular-stack.png" alt="Modular Blockchain Stack" /><br />
<em>Source: <a href="https://docs.celestia.org/">Celestia Documentation</a></em></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="10-summary">10. Summary</h2>

<p>Blockchain future encompasses technical scaling solutions, expanding application domains, regulatory maturation, và continued innovation. Modular architectures, zero-knowledge proofs, account abstraction, và cross-chain interoperability form technical foundation. Applications extend beyond finance into science, environment, social coordination, governance. Challenges include quantum computing threats, regulatory uncertainty, và user experience gaps.</p>

<p>Despite challenges, blockchain’s core value propositions - decentralization, transparency, programmable trust - increasingly relevant trong digital age valuing privacy, sovereignty, và censorship resistance. Understanding current trends và future directions positions participants at forefront của technology reshaping internet và finance fundamentally.</p>

<hr />

<p>✅ <strong>End of Lecture</strong></p>

<p>✅ <strong>End of Chapter 07 - Advanced Topics</strong></p>

<p>✅ <strong>END OF BLOCKCHAIN TECHNOLOGY COURSE</strong></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="references">References</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Buterin, V. (2021). <em>Endgame</em>. Vitalik’s Blog.</li>
  <li>Celestia. (2022). <em>Modular Blockchains: A Deep Dive</em>. Celestia Whitepaper.</li>
  <li>Buterin, V., et al. (2021). <em>ERC-4337: Account Abstraction</em>. Ethereum Improvement Proposals.</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name>Nguyen Le Linh</name><email>nglelinh@gmail.com</email></author><category term="contents" /><category term="vi" /><category term="chapter07" /><category term="blockchain-chapter07" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lecture: The Future of Blockchain - Trends và Innovations]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="vi"><title type="html">Lecture 07.04: Quantum Resistance Strategies for Blockchain</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/contents/vi/chapter07/blockchain-chapter07/07_04_Quantum_Resistance/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lecture 07.04: Quantum Resistance Strategies for Blockchain" /><published>2021-01-08T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2021-01-08T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/contents/vi/chapter07/blockchain-chapter07/07_04_Quantum_Resistance</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/contents/vi/chapter07/blockchain-chapter07/07_04_Quantum_Resistance/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="lecture-quantum-resistance-strategies-for-blockchain">Lecture: Quantum Resistance Strategies for Blockchain</h1>

<h2 id="1-concept-overview">1. Concept Overview</h2>

<p>Quantum computing threat necessitates proactive migration strategies for blockchain ecosystems. This lecture examines practical approaches blockchains can adopt preparing for quantum era, including hybrid signature schemes, gradual migration paths, emergency response plans, và protocol-level modifications enabling quantum-safe operations whilst maintaining backward compatibility during transition period.</p>

<p>Migration complexity stems from blockchain immutability và coordination requirements. Unlike traditional software easily patched, blockchain protocols require network-wide consensus for changes. Billions in assets secured by current cryptography must transition safely without creating vulnerabilities during migration window.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="2-intuitive-understanding">2. Intuitive Understanding</h2>

<p>Quantum migration comparable to upgrading airplane engines mid-flight. Cannot land (stop blockchain), cannot risk engine failure (cryptographic break), must transition smoothly whilst maintaining continuous operation. Requires careful planning, redundancy (hybrid schemes), testing (testnets), và coordination (governance).</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="3-technical-foundation">3. Technical Foundation</h2>

<p><strong>Hybrid signature approach</strong> during transition:</p>

<pre><code class="language-solidity">contract QuantumSafeWallet {
    // Dual signatures required
    bytes32 public classicalPubKey;  // ECDSA
    bytes32 public quantumSafePubKey;  // Dilithium
    
    function executeTransaction(
        bytes memory classicalSig,
        bytes memory pqSig,
        bytes memory txData
    ) external {
        // Verify BOTH signatures
        require(verifyECDSA(txData, classicalSig), "Classical sig invalid");
        require(verifyDilithium(txData, pqSig), "PQ sig invalid");
        
        // Execute only if both valid
        // Provides security even if one scheme broken
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Migration phases:</p>
<ol>
  <li><strong>Phase 1</strong>: Add post-quantum as optional (testing)</li>
  <li><strong>Phase 2</strong>: Require both signatures (transition)</li>
  <li><strong>Phase 3</strong>: Drop classical once quantum threat imminent</li>
</ol>

<hr />

<h2 id="4-mathematical--cryptographic-formulation">4. Mathematical / Cryptographic Formulation</h2>

<p>Security during transition period:</p>

<p>[
\text{Security}<em>{\text{hybrid}} = \max(\text{Security}</em>{\text{classical}}, \text{Security}_{\text{PQ}})
]</p>

<p>System secure as long as either scheme unbroken. Conservative approach ensuring continuity.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="5-implementation-insight">5. Implementation Insight</h2>

<p>Bitcoin quantum emergency plan: Soft fork freezing exposed public keys (addresses that spent), requiring quantum-safe signatures for movements, protecting unspent outputs with unexposed public keys (majority of Bitcoin).</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="6-common-challenges--attacks--trade-offs">6. Common Challenges / Attacks / Trade-offs</h2>

<p>Signature size doubles during hybrid period. Blockchain bandwidth constraints amplified. Must balance security (hybrid redundancy) versus efficiency (single scheme). Economic analysis determines optimal transition timing.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="7-related-concepts">7. Related Concepts</h2>

<p><strong>Quantum Key Distribution (QKD)</strong> provides alternative using quantum physics directly for secure communication. Impractical for blockchains (requires specialized hardware, point-to-point links) but demonstrates quantum technology’s dual nature - both threat và potential solution.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="8--fundamental-papers--whitepapers">8. ⭐ Fundamental Papers / Whitepapers</h2>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Paper</th>
      <th>Year</th>
      <th>Author(s)</th>
      <th>Contribution</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>“Quantum Attacks on Bitcoin”</strong></td>
      <td>2017</td>
      <td>Aggarwal et al.</td>
      <td>Bitcoin-specific quantum threat analysis</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>“Post-Quantum Blockchain Proofs of Work”</strong></td>
      <td>2019</td>
      <td>Sun et al.</td>
      <td>Quantum-safe mining</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<hr />

<h2 id="9--illustrations--visual-references">9. 🎨 Illustrations &amp; Visual References</h2>

<p><em>Source: <a href="https://csrc.nist.gov/Projects/post-quantum-cryptography">NIST Post-Quantum Cryptography</a></em></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="10-summary">10. Summary</h2>

<p>Quantum resistance requires proactive migration before quantum computers threaten current cryptography. Strategies include hybrid signatures providing defense-in-depth, phased migration minimizing disruption, và protocol modifications enabling quantum-safe operations. Understanding quantum threat timeline và preparation options essential for long-term blockchain security.</p>

<hr />

<p>✅ <strong>End of Lecture</strong></p>

<p>Next: Lecture 07.05 - Future of Blockchain Technology</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="references">References</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Aggarwal, D., et al. (2017). <em>Quantum attacks on Bitcoin</em>. Ledger, 2.</li>
  <li>NIST. (2024). <em>Post-Quantum Cryptography Project</em>. https://csrc.nist.gov/</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name>Nguyen Le Linh</name><email>nglelinh@gmail.com</email></author><category term="contents" /><category term="vi" /><category term="chapter07" /><category term="blockchain-chapter07" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lecture: Quantum Resistance Strategies for Blockchain]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="vi"><title type="html">Lecture 07.03: MEV - Maximal Extractable Value</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/contents/vi/chapter07/blockchain-chapter07/07_03_MEV/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lecture 07.03: MEV - Maximal Extractable Value" /><published>2021-01-08T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2021-01-08T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/contents/vi/chapter07/blockchain-chapter07/07_03_MEV</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/contents/vi/chapter07/blockchain-chapter07/07_03_MEV/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="lecture-mev---maximal-extractable-value">Lecture: MEV - Maximal Extractable Value</h1>

<h2 id="1-concept-overview">1. Concept Overview</h2>

<p>MEV (Maximal Extractable Value, formerly “Miner Extractable Value”) đại diện cho profit mà validators/miners có thể extract thông qua ability reorder, include, hoặc exclude transactions trong blocks they produce. Phenomenon này arose từ transparent mempool của Ethereum và deterministic execution của smart contracts, enabling sophisticated actors preview transaction effects và manipulate ordering for profit, often at expense của regular users.</p>

<p>MEV discovered và formalized bởi <strong>Phil Daian và colleagues</strong> trong paper “Flash Boys 2.0” năm 2019, drawing parallels với high-frequency trading trong traditional finance. Research showed billions of dollars extracted annually through techniques như front-running, back-running, và sandwich attacks, raising concerns về fairness, decentralization, và protocol stability.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="2-intuitive-understanding">2. Intuitive Understanding</h2>

<p>MEV comparable to insider trading trên stock market. Imagine seeing everyone’s orders before they execute, ability prioritize your own trades, và capacity rearrange order flow for maximum personal profit. Traditional finance heavily regulates này. Blockchain mempool inherently transparent - all pending transactions visible - creating MEV opportunities structurally embedded trong protocol design.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="3-technical-foundation">3. Technical Foundation</h2>

<p>Sandwich attack exemplifies MEV extraction. Bot detects large DEX trade trong mempool, front-runs bằng cách buying before victim (increasing price), victim’s trade executes at worse price, bot back-runs selling at profit.</p>

<div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">class</span> <span class="nc">MEVBot</span><span class="p">:</span>
    <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">detect_opportunity</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">self</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">pending_tx</span><span class="p">):</span>
        <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">pending_tx</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">type</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">==</span> <span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">DEX_SWAP</span><span class="sh">'</span> <span class="ow">and</span> <span class="n">pending_tx</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">amount</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="n">threshold</span><span class="p">:</span>
            <span class="c1"># Large trade detected - sandwich opportunity
</span>            <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">self</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">execute_sandwich</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">pending_tx</span><span class="p">)</span>
    
    <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">execute_sandwich</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">self</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">victim_tx</span><span class="p">):</span>
        <span class="c1"># Front-run: Buy before victim
</span>        <span class="n">front_run_tx</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">create_buy_tx</span><span class="p">(</span>
            <span class="n">amount</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">optimal_amount</span><span class="p">,</span>
            <span class="n">gas_price</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">victim_tx</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">gas_price</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span>  <span class="c1"># Higher priority
</span>        <span class="p">)</span>
        
        <span class="c1"># Victim tx executes (price increases)
</span>        
        <span class="c1"># Back-run: Sell after victim  
</span>        <span class="n">back_run_tx</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">create_sell_tx</span><span class="p">(</span>
            <span class="n">amount</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">front_run_amount</span><span class="p">,</span>
            <span class="n">gas_price</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">victim_tx</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">gas_price</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="mi">1</span>  <span class="c1"># Still processes
</span>        <span class="p">)</span>
        
        <span class="c1"># Profit = (price_after - price_before) * amount - gas_costs
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<hr />

<h2 id="4-mathematical--cryptographic-formulation">4. Mathematical / Cryptographic Formulation</h2>

<p>MEV extraction quantified as:</p>

<p>[
\text{MEV} = \max_{o \in O} R(o) - R(o_{\text{default}})
]</p>

<p>Where (O) = set của possible transaction orderings, (R(o)) = revenue under ordering (o).</p>

<p>Sandwich attack profit:</p>

<p>[
\Pi = (P_{\text{after}} - P_{\text{before}}) \times Q - \text{Gas}
]</p>

<p>Example: Victim buys 100 ETH on Uniswap, bot sandwiches:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Front-run 50 ETH: Price $2000 → $2020</li>
  <li>Victim 100 ETH: Price $2020 → $2060</li>
  <li>Back-run 50 ETH: Sell at $2060</li>
</ul>

<p>Profit: 50 × ($2060 - $2000) - gas ≈ $3,000</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="5-implementation-insight">5. Implementation Insight</h2>

<p><strong>Flashbots</strong> mitigates MEV through sealed-bid auctions:</p>

<div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c1"># Instead of public mempool, private transaction bundles
</span><span class="n">bundle</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">transactions</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="n">front_run_tx</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">victim_tx</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">back_run_tx</span><span class="p">],</span>
    <span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">block_number</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">target_block</span><span class="p">,</span>
    <span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">bribe</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="mf">0.1</span> <span class="n">ETH</span>  <span class="c1"># Paid to validator
</span><span class="p">}</span>

<span class="c1"># Submit directly to validator
# No public mempool exposure
# Reduces harmful MEV (though doesn't eliminate)
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<hr />

<h2 id="6-common-challenges--attacks--trade-offs">6. Common Challenges / Attacks / Trade-offs</h2>

<p>MEV creates centralization pressure - sophisticated infrastructure required, favoring large operators. Estimated $600M+ extracted annually, mostly by small number of entities. Threatens decentralization và fairness.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="7-related-concepts">7. Related Concepts</h2>

<p><strong>MEV-Boost</strong> enables validators outsource block building to specialized builders, separating proposing from building. Increases MEV extraction efficiency whilst maintaining decentralization of proposal rights.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="8--fundamental-papers--whitepapers">8. ⭐ Fundamental Papers / Whitepapers</h2>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Paper</th>
      <th>Year</th>
      <th>Author(s)</th>
      <th>Contribution</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>“Flash Boys 2.0: Frontrunning, Transaction Reordering, and Consensus Instability in Decentralized Exchanges”</strong></td>
      <td>2019</td>
      <td>Daian et al.</td>
      <td>MEV formalization</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>“Flashbots: Frontrunning the MEV Crisis”</strong></td>
      <td>2020</td>
      <td>Flashbots team</td>
      <td>MEV mitigation approach</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<hr />

<h2 id="9--illustrations--visual-references">9. 🎨 Illustrations &amp; Visual References</h2>

<p><img src="https://docs.flashbots.net/img/mev-extraction.png" alt="MEV Extraction Flow" /><br />
<em>Source: <a href="https://docs.flashbots.net/">Flashbots Documentation</a></em></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="10-summary">10. Summary</h2>

<p>MEV represents billions extracted through transaction ordering manipulation. While some MEV unavoidable (arbitrage beneficial for efficiency), harmful MEV (sandwich attacks) damages user experience và fairness. Solutions like Flashbots, encrypted mempools, và fair ordering protocols attempt mitigate whilst preserving validator economics. Understanding MEV essential for protocol designers, traders, và anyone interacting with DeFi.</p>

<hr />

<p>✅ <strong>End of Lecture</strong></p>

<p>Next: Lecture 07.04 - Quantum Resistance Strategies</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="references">References</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Daian, P., et al. (2019). <em>Flash Boys 2.0</em>. IEEE S&amp;P 2020.</li>
  <li>Flashbots. (2020). <em>Flashbots Documentation</em>. https://docs.flashbots.net/</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name>Nguyen Le Linh</name><email>nglelinh@gmail.com</email></author><category term="contents" /><category term="vi" /><category term="chapter07" /><category term="blockchain-chapter07" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lecture: MEV - Maximal Extractable Value]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="vi"><title type="html">Lecture 07.01: NFTs và Digital Ownership - Non-Fungible Tokens</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/contents/vi/chapter07/blockchain-chapter07/07_01_NFTs_Digital_Ownership/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lecture 07.01: NFTs và Digital Ownership - Non-Fungible Tokens" /><published>2021-01-08T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2021-01-08T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/contents/vi/chapter07/blockchain-chapter07/07_01_NFTs_Digital_Ownership</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/deep-learning-self-learning/contents/vi/chapter07/blockchain-chapter07/07_01_NFTs_Digital_Ownership/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="lecture-nfts-và-digital-ownership---non-fungible-tokens">Lecture: NFTs và Digital Ownership - Non-Fungible Tokens</h1>

<h2 id="1-concept-overview">1. Concept Overview</h2>

<p>Non-Fungible Tokens, hay NFTs, đại diện cho một paradigm shift fundamental trong cách chúng ta conceptualize ownership trong digital realm. Trước blockchain, digital assets luôn có một vấn đề bản chất: chúng có thể được copy perfectly với zero cost. Một file MP3, một bức ảnh digital, một tài liệu - tất cả đều có thể được duplicate infinitely. Điều này tạo ra một tension giữa abundance của digital goods và scarcity cần thiết cho economic value.</p>

<p>NFTs giải quyết vấn đề này bằng cách tạo ra <strong>provable scarcity</strong> và <strong>verifiable ownership</strong> cho digital assets thông qua blockchain technology. Concept cốt lõi là mỗi NFT là một unique token trên blockchain, không thể được exchanged one-to-one với token khác (non-fungible), và ownership history được tracked permanently và transparently. Điều này transform digital items từ infinitely copyable sang uniquely ownable, opening up entirely new categories của digital commerce và creative expression.</p>

<p>Historical context của NFTs bắt đầu sớm hơn nhiều người nghĩ. Năm 2012, <strong>Colored Coins</strong> trên Bitcoin đã attempt represent real-world assets on-chain. Năm 2014, <strong>Counterparty</strong> platform cho phép create custom tokens. Nhưng NFT movement thực sự bắt đầu năm 2017 với <strong>CryptoPunks</strong> - 10,000 unique pixel art characters được generate algorithmically và distributed free trên Ethereum. Cùng năm đó, <strong>CryptoKitties</strong> exploded, một game cho phép breed và trade digital cats, congesting Ethereum network và demonstrating demand for digital collectibles.</p>

<p>Năm 2021 witnessed NFT boom unprecedented. Artist <strong>Beeple</strong> bán một NFT artwork với giá $69 million tại Christie’s auction house, marking first time một major auction house sold purely digital art. <strong>Bored Ape Yacht Club</strong> became cultural phenomenon, với celebrities và brands rushing to acquire these profile pictures. Trading volume reached billions of dollars monthly, và NFT expanded far beyond art into domains như gaming, music, real estate, identity, và credentials.</p>

<p>Nhưng NFTs không chỉ là speculation bubble hay digital art craze. Chúng represent một innovation fundamental: <strong>programmable ownership</strong>. Traditional ownership requires legal systems, title offices, và trusted intermediaries để enforce. NFT ownership được enforce bởi code và cryptography, enabling new forms của fractional ownership, royalty automation, và composable digital assets. Một musician có thể embed royalty logic directly vào NFT, ensuring họ receive percentage mỗi khi NFT được resold. A game item có thể exist across multiple games. Digital identity credentials có thể be self-sovereign và verifiable.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="2-intuitive-understanding">2. Intuitive Understanding</h2>

<p>Để hiểu NFTs deeply, hãy contrast với fungible tokens. Fungibility là property rằng mọi unit của asset đều identical và interchangeable. Một dollar bill có thể được exchanged với any other dollar bill without loss of value. Bitcoin và Ethereum đều fungible - mỗi BTC hay ETH giống hệt nhau về function và value. Điều này perfect cho currency, nhưng terrible cho representing unique items.</p>

<p>Hãy tưởng tượng bạn sở hữu một bức tranh nổi tiếng - ví dụ Mona Lisa. Bức tranh này unique, có provenance specific, và value không thể được reduced thành exchange rate. Bạn không thể “split” Mona Lisa thành smaller equivalent pieces. Bạn không thể exchange nó one-to-one với any other painting. Đây chính là non-fungibility - uniqueness và non-interchangeability.</p>

<p>NFTs bring concept này vào digital world. Thay vì represent uniform units of value như ERC-20 tokens, NFTs represent unique items. Mỗi NFT có một token ID duy nhất, có thể have metadata associated (image, description, properties), và ownership được tracked separately. Khi bạn own một CryptoPunk NFT, bạn không own “một unit of CryptoPunks” - bạn own <strong>that specific CryptoPunk với specific attributes</strong>. Nó như owning painting #5432 trong collection, không thể confused với painting #5433.</p>

<p>Visual mental model hữu ích là nghĩ về NFTs như <strong>digital certificates of authenticity</strong>. Trong art world, certificates of authenticity accompany expensive artworks để prove provenance và authenticity. NFTs serve similar function nhưng với advantages profound. Traditional certificates có thể be forged, lost, disputed. NFT certificates exist on blockchain, impossible to forge (cryptographically secured), impossible to lose (always on-chain), và impossible to dispute (transparent ownership history). Moreover, NFT itself CAN contain hoặc point to the digital asset, creating inseparable link giữa certificate và artwork.</p>

<p>Smart contract functionality thêm một dimension entirely new. NFTs không chỉ represent ownership - chúng có thể contain <strong>programmable logic</strong>. Một NFT ticket có thể automatically expire after event. Một NFT song có thể pay artist percentage mỗi time được resold. Một NFT game item có thể level up based on usage. Đây là <strong>smart property</strong> - assets với built-in rules và behaviors, không require external enforcement.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="3-technical-foundation">3. Technical Foundation</h2>

<p>NFT standards trên Ethereum được define through ERCs (Ethereum Request for Comments). Standard fundamental nhất là <strong>ERC-721</strong>, proposed bởi <strong>William Entriken, Dieter Shirley, Jacob Evans, và Nastassia Sachs</strong> năm 2018. ERC-721 defines minimal interface mà NFT contract phải implement để be interoperable với wallets, marketplaces, và other contracts.</p>

<p>Core functions của ERC-721 include <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">balanceOf</code>, which returns number of NFTs owned bởi address; <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ownerOf</code>, which returns owner của specific token ID; <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">transferFrom</code>, which transfers ownership; <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">approve</code>, which authorizes another address to transfer specific NFT; và <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">safeTransferFrom</code>, which safely transfers với check rằng recipient có thể handle NFTs. Importantly, mỗi token được identify bởi unique <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">uint256</code> token ID, allowing representation của up to 2^256 different unique items.</p>

<p>Metadata handling trong NFTs typically follows pattern này: contract stores base URI và token ID maps to specific metadata file. Metadata thường stored off-chain (IPFS, Arweave, hoặc centralized server) vì storing large data on-chain prohibitively expensive. Ví dụ, CryptoPunk image itself không stored on Ethereum - chỉ có reference đến image. Điều này creates tension: NFT ownership on-chain permanent, nhưng actual content may not be. Best practices recommend decentralized storage (IPFS với content addressing) để ensure persistence.</p>

<p>ERC-1155, proposed bởi <strong>Enjin team</strong>, extends NFT concept bằng cách allowing <strong>multi-token standard</strong>. Single ERC-1155 contract có thể manage multiple token types - both fungible và non-fungible. Điều này particularly useful cho gaming, where you might have thousands of unique items plus fungible currencies. Gas efficiency improved significantly vì batch transfers possible. Ví dụ, transferring 100 different items có thể done trong single transaction thay vì 100 separate transactions như ERC-721 requires.</p>

<p>NFT composition patterns đã evolved sophisticated. <strong>Nested NFTs</strong> allow one NFT to own other NFTs - ví dụ, character NFT owning weapon NFTs. <strong>Fractionalized NFTs</strong> split expensive NFT thành multiple fungible shares, enabling collective ownership. <strong>Dynamic NFTs</strong> change metadata based on external conditions - sports NFT updating với player statistics, game character NFT leveling up. <strong>Soulbound Tokens (SBTs)</strong> proposed bởi Vitalik Buterin represent non-transferable NFTs for identity và credentials - once issued, cannot be sold hoặc transferred, only revoked by issuer.</p>

<p>Contract architecture for NFTs typically separates concerns. Main contract handles ownership tracking và transfers. Metadata contract or service provides token information. Marketplace contracts facilitate buying/selling. Royalty contracts ensure creators receive percentage on secondary sales. This modularity enables ecosystem evolution - new marketplaces can emerge without requiring new token contracts, và existing NFTs remain compatible.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="4-mathematical--cryptographic-formulation">4. Mathematical / Cryptographic Formulation</h2>

<p>NFT uniqueness mathematically guaranteed through token ID space. Với <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">uint256</code> token IDs, total possible unique tokens is:</p>

<p>[
N_{\max} = 2^{256} \approx 1.16 \times 10^{77}
]</p>

<p>Đây là số lớn hơn estimated số atoms trong observable universe (approximately (10^{80})). Practically unlimited uniqueness space, ensuring no collision concerns trong design space.</p>

<p>Ownership verification trong NFTs relies on same cryptographic primitives như fungible tokens. Given NFT contract (C) và token ID (t), ownership query (\text{ownerOf}(t)) returns address (A). To prove ownership, holder of address (A) must demonstrate knowledge của private key corresponding đến (A)’s public key. This follows ECDSA signature scheme discussed in earlier lectures, với security reduced to discrete logarithm problem on elliptic curves.</p>

<p>Transfer safety được ensure through multiple mechanisms. Basic <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">transferFrom</code> function simply changes ownership mapping:</p>

<p>[
\text{owner}[t] \leftarrow A_{\text{new}} \quad \text{(atomic state update)}
]</p>

<p>However, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">safeTransferFrom</code> adds verification step. Before transferring, contract calls recipient với selector <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">onERC721Received</code>:</p>

<p>[
\text{if recipient is contract: require}(recipient.\text{onERC721Received}(…) = \text{MAGIC_VALUE})
]</p>

<p>This prevents accidental transfers đến contracts không equipped để handle NFTs, avoiding permanent loss. Magic value <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">0x150b7a02</code> serves như confirmation rằng contract implements proper interface.</p>

<p>Royalty mathematics trong ERC-2981 standard defines royalty info function:</p>

<p>[
(\text{receiver}, \text{royaltyAmount}) = \text{royaltyInfo}(\text{tokenId}, \text{salePrice})
]</p>

<p>Where:</p>

<p>[
\text{royaltyAmount} = \text{salePrice} \times \frac{\text{royaltyBasisPoints}}{10000}
]</p>

<p>Ví dụ, với 5% royalty (500 basis points) và sale price 10 ETH:</p>

<p>[
\text{royaltyAmount} = 10 \times \frac{500}{10000} = 0.5 \text{ ETH}
]</p>

<p>Creator automatically receives 0.5 ETH mỗi sale.</p>

<p>Rarity trong generative NFT projects often follows statistical distributions. For collection với (n) traits, each trait có (m_i) variants, total possible combinations:</p>

<p>[
C = \prod_{i=1}^{n} m_i
]</p>

<p>For CryptoPunks với 7 attributes (type, hair, eyes, etc.), mỗi có variable number of options, total combinations exceed collection size (10,000), ensuring uniqueness. Rarity score thường calculated as:</p>

<p>[
R(t) = \sum_{i=1}^{k} \frac{1}{f_i}
]</p>

<p>Where (f_i) là frequency của trait (i) in collection. Rare traits contribute more to overall rarity score.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="5-implementation-insight">5. Implementation Insight</h2>

<pre><code class="language-solidity">// SPDX-License-Identifier: MIT
pragma solidity ^0.8.20;

import "@openzeppelin/contracts/token/ERC721/ERC721.sol";
import "@openzeppelin/contracts/token/ERC721/extensions/ERC721URIStorage.sol";
import "@openzeppelin/contracts/access/Ownable.sol";
import "@openzeppelin/contracts/utils/Counters.sol";

/**
 * @title Complete NFT Implementation with Advanced Features
 * @dev Includes: Minting, Metadata, Royalties, Enumeration
 */
contract AdvancedNFT is ERC721, ERC721URIStorage, Ownable {
    using Counters for Counters.Counter;
    
    Counters.Counter private _tokenIds;
    
    // Royalty info (ERC-2981 standard)
    address public royaltyReceiver;
    uint96 public royaltyBasisPoints = 500; // 5% default
    
    // Metadata
    string private _baseTokenURI;
    mapping(uint256 =&gt; string) private _tokenURIs;
    
    // Supply tracking
    uint256 public constant MAX_SUPPLY = 10000;
    
    // Events
    event NFTMinted(address indexed to, uint256 indexed tokenId, string tokenURI);
    event RoyaltySet(address indexed receiver, uint96 basisPoints);
    
    constructor(
        string memory name,
        string memory symbol,
        string memory baseURI,
        address _royaltyReceiver
    ) ERC721(name, symbol) {
        _baseTokenURI = baseURI;
        royaltyReceiver = _royaltyReceiver;
    }
    
    /**
     * @dev Mint new NFT
     */
    function mintNFT(address recipient, string memory metadataURI) 
        public 
        onlyOwner 
        returns (uint256) 
    {
        _tokenIds.increment();
        uint256 newTokenId = _tokenIds.current();
        
        require(newTokenId &lt;= MAX_SUPPLY, "Max supply reached");
        
        _safeMint(recipient, newTokenId);
        _setTokenURI(newTokenId, metadataURI);
        
        emit NFTMinted(recipient, newTokenId, metadataURI);
        
        return newTokenId;
    }
    
    /**
     * @dev Batch mint (gas efficient)
     */
    function batchMint(address[] memory recipients, string[] memory metadataURIs) 
        public 
        onlyOwner 
    {
        require(recipients.length == metadataURIs.length, "Length mismatch");
        require(_tokenIds.current() + recipients.length &lt;= MAX_SUPPLY, "Exceeds max supply");
        
        for (uint256 i = 0; i &lt; recipients.length; i++) {
            _tokenIds.increment();
            uint256 tokenId = _tokenIds.current();
            
            _safeMint(recipients[i], tokenId);
            _setTokenURI(tokenId, metadataURIs[i]);
            
            emit NFTMinted(recipients[i], tokenId, metadataURIs[i]);
        }
    }
    
    /**
     * @dev Set royalty info
     */
    function setRoyaltyInfo(address receiver, uint96 basisPoints) public onlyOwner {
        require(basisPoints &lt;= 10000, "Royalty too high"); // Max 100%
        royaltyReceiver = receiver;
        royaltyBasisPoints = basisPoints;
        
        emit RoyaltySet(receiver, basisPoints);
    }
    
    /**
     * @dev ERC-2981 royalty info
     */
    function royaltyInfo(uint256 tokenId, uint256 salePrice)
        external
        view
        returns (address receiver, uint256 royaltyAmount)
    {
        require(_exists(tokenId), "Token doesn't exist");
        
        royaltyAmount = (salePrice * royaltyBasisPoints) / 10000;
        return (royaltyReceiver, royaltyAmount);
    }
    
    /**
     * @dev Get base URI
     */
    function _baseURI() internal view override returns (string memory) {
        return _baseTokenURI;
    }
    
    /**
     * @dev Set base URI
     */
    function setBaseURI(string memory baseURI) public onlyOwner {
        _baseTokenURI = baseURI;
    }
    
    /**
     * @dev Get total supply
     */
    function totalSupply() public view returns (uint256) {
        return _tokenIds.current();
    }
    
    /**
     * @dev Check if token exists
     */
    function exists(uint256 tokenId) public view returns (bool) {
        return _exists(tokenId);
    }
    
    /**
     * @dev Token URI override for ERC721URIStorage
     */
    function tokenURI(uint256 tokenId)
        public
        view
        override(ERC721, ERC721URIStorage)
        returns (string memory)
    {
        return super.tokenURI(tokenId);
    }
    
    /**
     * @dev Supports interface (for marketplace compatibility)
     */
    function supportsInterface(bytes4 interfaceId)
        public
        view
        override(ERC721, ERC721URIStorage)
        returns (bool)
    {
        return interfaceId == 0x2a55205a // ERC-2981 royalty
            || super.supportsInterface(interfaceId);
    }
    
    /**
     * @dev Burn NFT
     */
    function burn(uint256 tokenId) public {
        require(_isApprovedOrOwner(msg.sender, tokenId), "Not owner or approved");
        _burn(tokenId);
    }
    
    // Override required functions
    function _burn(uint256 tokenId) internal override(ERC721, ERC721URIStorage) {
        super._burn(tokenId);
    }
}

/**
 * @title NFT Marketplace
 * @dev Simple marketplace for buying/selling NFTs
 */
contract NFTMarketplace {
    struct Listing {
        address seller;
        address nftContract;
        uint256 tokenId;
        uint256 price;
        bool active;
    }
    
    mapping(bytes32 =&gt; Listing) public listings;
    uint256 public constant MARKETPLACE_FEE = 250; // 2.5%
    
    event Listed(
        bytes32 indexed listingId,
        address indexed seller,
        address indexed nftContract,
        uint256 tokenId,
        uint256 price
    );
    
    event Sold(
        bytes32 indexed listingId,
        address indexed buyer,
        uint256 price
    );
    
    event Delisted(bytes32 indexed listingId);
    
    /**
     * @dev List NFT for sale
     */
    function listNFT(
        address nftContract,
        uint256 tokenId,
        uint256 price
    ) public returns (bytes32) {
        require(price &gt; 0, "Price must be &gt; 0");
        
        // Verify ownership
        IERC721 nft = IERC721(nftContract);
        require(nft.ownerOf(tokenId) == msg.sender, "Not owner");
        
        // Verify approval
        require(
            nft.isApprovedForAll(msg.sender, address(this)) ||
            nft.getApproved(tokenId) == address(this),
            "Marketplace not approved"
        );
        
        // Create listing ID
        bytes32 listingId = keccak256(
            abi.encodePacked(nftContract, tokenId, msg.sender, block.timestamp)
        );
        
        listings[listingId] = Listing({
            seller: msg.sender,
            nftContract: nftContract,
            tokenId: tokenId,
            price: price,
            active: true
        });
        
        emit Listed(listingId, msg.sender, nftContract, tokenId, price);
        
        return listingId;
    }
    
    /**
     * @dev Buy NFT
     */
    function buyNFT(bytes32 listingId) public payable {
        Listing storage listing = listings[listingId];
        
        require(listing.active, "Listing not active");
        require(msg.value &gt;= listing.price, "Insufficient payment");
        
        // Mark as inactive
        listing.active = false;
        
        // Calculate fees
        uint256 marketplaceFee = (listing.price * MARKETPLACE_FEE) / 10000;
        uint256 sellerProceeds = listing.price - marketplaceFee;
        
        // Check royalty (ERC-2981)
        (address royaltyReceiver, uint256 royaltyAmount) = 
            IERC2981(listing.nftContract).royaltyInfo(listing.tokenId, listing.price);
        
        if (royaltyAmount &gt; 0) {
            sellerProceeds -= royaltyAmount;
            payable(royaltyReceiver).transfer(royaltyAmount);
        }
        
        // Transfer NFT
        IERC721(listing.nftContract).safeTransferFrom(
            listing.seller,
            msg.sender,
            listing.tokenId
        );
        
        // Pay seller
        payable(listing.seller).transfer(sellerProceeds);
        
        // Refund excess
        if (msg.value &gt; listing.price) {
            payable(msg.sender).transfer(msg.value - listing.price);
        }
        
        emit Sold(listingId, msg.sender, listing.price);
    }
    
    /**
     * @dev Delist NFT
     */
    function delistNFT(bytes32 listingId) public {
        Listing storage listing = listings[listingId];
        
        require(listing.active, "Listing not active");
        require(listing.seller == msg.sender, "Not seller");
        
        listing.active = false;
        
        emit Delisted(listingId);
    }
    
    /**
     * @dev Withdraw marketplace fees (owner only)
     */
    function withdrawFees() public {
        payable(owner()).transfer(address(this).balance);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Real-world implementations như OpenSea, Rarible, và Foundation build on these primitives nhưng add features extensive như collection verification, lazy minting (mint only when sold), auctions (English, Dutch), bundles, và cross-chain support. Gas optimizations critical - high-volume collections use techniques như ERC721A (Azuki’s optimization enabling batch minting at near-singular gas cost) và merkle proofs for allowlists.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="6-common-challenges--attacks--trade-offs">6. Common Challenges / Attacks / Trade-offs</h2>

<p>NFT ecosystem faces numerous challenges requiring careful consideration. Metadata permanence remains contentious issue. Khi NFT points đến off-chain resource via HTTP URL, resource có thể disappear if server goes down. IPFS provides improvement through content addressing - URL derived from file hash, ensuring retrievability as long as anyone pins content - nhưng không guarantee permanent availability. Arweave attempts solve này through permanent storage model với upfront payment, but economic sustainability remains unproven long-term.</p>

<p>Smart contract bugs trong NFT contracts particularly dangerous given value at risk. Phishing attacks common - malicious contracts mimicking legitimate ones, tricking users into approving unauthorized transfers. Approval mechanisms trong ERC-721 create attack surface: calling <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">setApprovalForAll</code> grants contract permission to transfer ALL of user’s NFTs from that collection. Users frequently unaware of this risk, approving malicious contracts.</p>

<p>Wash trading manipulates NFT prices through self-dealing. Attacker owns NFT, sells to themselves từ different wallet at inflated price, creating appearance of legitimate sale. This inflates floor price metrics và misleads buyers. On-chain analysis can detect patterns but difficult to prevent entirely. Marketplaces implement heuristics như flagging rapid back-and-forth sales between wallets, nhưng sophisticated wash traders adapt.</p>

<p>Copyright và intellectual property issues pervade NFT space. Owning NFT typically không grant copyright to underlying work unless explicitly stated. Buyer owns token on blockchain nhưng creator retains IP rights. This confusing for many users expecting full ownership. Additionally, anyone có thể mint NFT pointing đến content they don’t own - plagiarism rampant. Verification systems như Twitter Blue checkmarks for verified collections attempt address này, but remain centralized solutions.</p>

<p>Royalty enforcement shows technical limitations of decentralized systems. ERC-2981 standard defines royalty interface, nhưng enforcement requires marketplace cooperation. Nothing prevents direct wallet-to-wallet transfer bypassing royalties entirely. Marketplaces voluntarily honor royalties, but cannot be forced on-chain. Proposals like ERC-4910 (royalty-enforced NFTs) attempt make royalties mandatory through transfer restrictions, but this limits composability và faces adoption challenges.</p>

<p>Environmental concerns about NFT energy consumption largely addressed through Ethereum’s Merge to Proof-of-Stake. Pre-merge, minting NFT on Ethereum consumed approximately 200 kWh (carbon footprint of 100 kg CO2). Post-merge, energy consumption reduced 99.95%, making NFT carbon footprint comparable to sending email. However, perception issues remain, và some artists still avoid NFTs for environmental reasons.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="7-related-concepts">7. Related Concepts</h2>

<p>NFTs exist within broader ecosystem của digital ownership innovations. <strong>Decentralized Identity (DID)</strong> leverages NFT-like tokens for self-sovereign identity credentials. Rather than identity document issued by government và stored in database, DIDs enable individuals hold verifiable credentials as tokens, presenting proofs without revealing underlying data. This connects to <strong>Soulbound Tokens (SBTs)</strong> concept proposed by Vitalik Buterin, Glen Weyl, và Puja Ohlhaver - non-transferable tokens representing achievements, credentials, hoặc memberships, creating <strong>Decentralized Society (DeSoc)</strong>.</p>

<p><strong>Fractionalization</strong> creates fascinating intersection between NFTs và DeFi. Platforms như Fractional.art allow expensive NFT be split thành fungible ERC-20 shares, enabling collective ownership và liquid markets for otherwise illiquid assets. Mathematics straightforward: NFT locked in vault contract, vault issues (n) shares, each representing (1/n) ownership. Buyout mechanisms allow anyone purchase all shares at threshold price, retrieving original NFT.</p>

<p><strong>Dynamic NFTs</strong> blur line giữa static collectibles và evolving digital entities. Using <strong>Chainlink oracles</strong>, NFT metadata can update based on real-world events. Sports player NFT could reflect current season statistics, updated automatically. Weather NFT could change appearance based on actual weather data. This requires careful contract design separating immutable aspects (ownership, provenance) from mutable (metadata URI, properties).</p>

<p><strong>NFT standards comparison</strong> reveals design tradeoffs. ERC-721 optimized cho unique items, simple interface, but expensive cho large collections. ERC-1155 enables batch operations, mixing fungible và non-fungible, reducing gas substantially for games và metaverses. ERC-998 (Composable NFTs) allows NFTs own other tokens, creating hierarchies - parent NFT sold includes all children automatically. Each standard serves different use cases, và choosing appropriate standard critical for project success.</p>

<p><strong>Cross-chain NFTs</strong> represent next frontier. Projects like Axie Infinity initially on Ethereum, migrated to Ronin sidechain for scalability. Omnichain NFTs (LayerZero) enable single NFT exist across multiple chains simultaneously. User bridges NFT between chains as needed, maintaining unified identity. This requires sophisticated cross-chain messaging và handling of edge cases like conflicting states.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="8--fundamental-papers--whitepapers">8. ⭐ Fundamental Papers / Whitepapers</h2>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Paper</th>
      <th>Year</th>
      <th>Author(s)</th>
      <th>Contribution</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>“ERC-721: Non-Fungible Token Standard”</strong></td>
      <td>2018</td>
      <td>William Entriken, Dieter Shirley, Jacob Evans, Nastassia Sachs</td>
      <td>Defined NFT standard for Ethereum</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>“ERC-1155: Multi Token Standard”</strong></td>
      <td>2018</td>
      <td>Witek Radomski, Andrew Cooke, Philippe Castonguay, et al.</td>
      <td>Multi-token standard for gaming/metaverse</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>“ERC-998: Composable Non-Fungible Token Standard”</strong></td>
      <td>2018</td>
      <td>Matt Lockyer, Nick Mudge</td>
      <td>NFTs owning other tokens</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>“Decentralized Society: Finding Web3’s Soul”</strong></td>
      <td>2022</td>
      <td>E. Glen Weyl, Puja Ohlhaver, Vitalik Buterin</td>
      <td>Soulbound tokens for identity</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>“ERC-2981: NFT Royalty Standard”</strong></td>
      <td>2020</td>
      <td>Zach Burks, James Morgan, Blaine Malone, James Seibel</td>
      <td>Standardized royalty interface</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>“ERC-4907: Rental NFT, Extension for ERC-721”</strong></td>
      <td>2022</td>
      <td>Anders, Lance, Shrug</td>
      <td>Separates ownership from usage rights</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>“Art Blocks: On-Chain Generative Art”</strong></td>
      <td>2020</td>
      <td>Erick Calderon (Snowfro)</td>
      <td>Algorithmic art generation on Ethereum</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>“The Non-Fungible Token Bible”</strong></td>
      <td>2020</td>
      <td>OpenSea team</td>
      <td>Comprehensive NFT guide</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<hr />

<h2 id="9--illustrations--visual-references">9. 🎨 Illustrations &amp; Visual References</h2>

<h3 id="block-structure">Block Structure</h3>
<p><img src="https://ethereum.org/static/7f6b2b6e0c8b4e7f8d5e9a3c2b1f0e8d/nft-diagram.png" alt="Ethereum NFT Transaction Flow" /><br />
<em>Source: <a href="https://ethereum.org/en/nft/">Ethereum.org - NFT Documentation</a></em></p>

<h3 id="merkle-tree">Merkle Tree</h3>
<p><img src="https://docs.opensea.io/img/metadata-structure.png" alt="NFT Metadata Structure" /><br />
<em>Source: <a href="https://docs.opensea.io/docs/metadata-standards">OpenSea Metadata Standards</a></em></p>

<h3 id="erc-721-vs-erc-1155">ERC-721 vs ERC-1155</h3>
<p>| Feature | ERC-721 | ERC-1155 |
|———|———|———-|
| Token uniqueness | One token ID = one unique item | Multiple tokens per ID possible |
| Batch transfers | No (one by one) | Yes (efficient batching) |
| Fungible + Non-fungible | Separate contracts needed | Same contract handles both |
| Gas efficiency | Lower (individual operations) | Higher (batch operations) |
| Use case | Art, collectibles | Gaming, metaverse |</p>

<p><em>Source: <a href="https://eips.ethereum.org/">Ethereum EIP Repository</a></em></p>

<h3 id="interactive-tools">Interactive Tools</h3>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://opensea.io/">OpenSea</a> - Largest NFT marketplace, explore collections</li>
  <li><a href="https://etherscan.io/nft-top-contracts">Etherscan NFT Tracker</a> - On-chain NFT analytics</li>
  <li><a href="https://ipfs.io/">IPFS</a> - Decentralized storage for metadata</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.arweave.org/">Arweave</a> - Permanent storage solution</li>
  <li><a href="https://rarible.com/">Rarible</a> - Create and trade NFTs</li>
  <li><a href="https://zora.co/">Zora</a> - NFT protocol and marketplace</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="10-summary-và-key-takeaways">10. Summary và Key Takeaways</h2>

<p>NFTs represent paradigm shift in digital ownership, creating verifiable scarcity và programmable property rights cho digital assets through blockchain technology. Core innovation lies trong ability to prove ownership cryptographically without requiring centralized authority, enabled by smart contract standards như ERC-721 và ERC-1155. These standards define interfaces allowing NFTs be universally recognized across wallets, marketplaces, và applications, creating composable ecosystem.</p>

<p>Technical implementation builds on Ethereum’s account model và EVM execution environment. Unique token IDs within 256-bit space provide effectively unlimited uniqueness, while ownership tracked via mapping data structure in contract storage. Transfer mechanisms incorporate safety checks preventing accidental loss, và approval systems enable delegated management. Metadata handling typically hybrid - contract on-chain points to off-chain resources via URIs, balancing cost với functionality.</p>

<p>Mathematical foundations ensure security và uniqueness. Cryptographic signatures prove ownership, collision resistance của hash functions guarantee token ID uniqueness, và Merkle proofs enable efficient verification. Royalty calculations embedded in contracts enable creators earn from secondary market automatically, though enforcement depends on marketplace cooperation rather than protocol-level guarantees.</p>

<p>Challenges include metadata permanence concerns, copyright confusion, wash trading manipulation, và scalability limitations. Solutions emerging through improved storage solutions (IPFS, Arweave), better verification systems, marketplace standards, và Layer 2 scaling. NFT applications extending far beyond digital art into gaming, music, credentials, real estate tokenization, và decentralized identity.</p>

<p>Future directions include dynamic NFTs responding to real-world data, fractionalization enabling collective ownership, cross-chain NFTs operating across multiple blockchains, và soulbound tokens for non-transferable credentials. NFT ecosystem continues evolving rapidly, với new standards, tools, và use cases emerging continuously. Understanding NFT fundamentals - from ERC standards to marketplace mechanics to security considerations - essential for anyone building in Web3 space.</p>

<hr />

<p>✅ <strong>End of Lecture</strong></p>

<p>Next: Lecture 07.02 - Web3 Infrastructure và Decentralized Storage</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="references">References</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Entriken, W., Shirley, D., Evans, J., &amp; Sachs, N. (2018). <em>ERC-721: Non-Fungible Token Standard</em>. Ethereum Improvement Proposals.</li>
  <li>Radomski, W., Cooke, A., Castonguay, P., et al. (2018). <em>ERC-1155: Multi Token Standard</em>. Ethereum Improvement Proposals.</li>
  <li>Weyl, E. G., Ohlhaver, P., &amp; Buterin, V. (2022). <em>Decentralized Society: Finding Web3’s Soul</em>. arXiv preprint.</li>
  <li>OpenSea Documentation. (2024). <em>NFT Metadata Standards</em>. https://docs.opensea.io/</li>
  <li>Ethereum.org. (2024). <em>Non-Fungible Tokens (NFT)</em>. https://ethereum.org/en/nft/</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name>Nguyen Le Linh</name><email>nglelinh@gmail.com</email></author><category term="contents" /><category term="vi" /><category term="chapter07" /><category term="blockchain-chapter07" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lecture: NFTs và Digital Ownership - Non-Fungible Tokens]]></summary></entry></feed>